Guide to the Eugene A. Carroll Papers, 1890-2014 (bulk 1944-2014)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Eugene A. Carroll Papers
1890-2014
1944-2014
Carroll, Eugene A.
12.5 cubic feet (14 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The Eugene A. Carroll Papers document Carroll's academic career as an art historian, curator, writer, as well as his involvement as executor of the William K. Rose estate. The papers contain professional and personal correspondence and include letters documenting Carroll's relationship with his partner, William K. Rose, during the 1960s. The W.K. Rose material also includes photographic prints, travel journals, a limited volume of subject files and writings by Rose, and one audio tape interview. The Carroll Papers contain subject files, including teaching and research reference materials, travel files, datebooks, writings by Carroll, correspondence with colleagues, friends, and Rose, as well as a limited volume of correspondence from Carroll to his parents. Holdings also include journals, photographic prints, and documentation regarding the management of the Rose estate and Vassar's W.K. Rose fellowship.
Biographical Note
Eugene A. Carroll, scholar of 16th century Italian Renaissance artist Rosso Fiorentino, was born in St. Louis, Missouri in 1931. Carroll was a professor of Art History at Vassar College from 1965 to 1999, serving as chair of the department from 1980 to 1983. He received a PhD from Harvard University in Art History (1964), and an M.A. in the History of Art from Harvard University (1958). He completed a Fulbright Scholarship in Florence, Italy in 1955, a fellowship at the American Academy in Rome (1958), and was later awarded membership at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton (1983). Carroll curated and wrote the catalogue for the exhibition, Rosso Fiorentino: Drawing Prints, and Decorative Arts, at the National Gallery of Art, Washington D.C. in 1987. His partner, William K. Rose (1924-1968) was a professor of English at Vassar College.
Bibliography
Books:
The Print Images of Rosso Fiorentino, Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, University of California, Los Angeles, 1989.
Rosso Fiorentino, Drawings, Prints, and Decorative Arts, National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., 1987.
The Drawings of Rosso Fiorentino, Garland Press, New York, 1976.
Articles and Reviews:
"On Rosso's Volterra Deposition and Other Tragedies," Acts of the Seminario di Studio, Il Pontormo e Il Rosso a Volterra, Empoli and Volterra, 22-24 September 1994, Marsilio Editori, Venice, 1995.
"Printmaking in Renaissance France," review of The French Renaissance in Prints from the Bibliotheque Nationale de France, exhibition catalogue, UCLA at the Armand Hammer Museum of Art and Cultural Center, Los Angeles, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, Bibliotheque Nationale, Paris, 1994-1995, Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, University of California, Los Angeles, 1994, in Print Quarterly, London, 1995.
Review of Eric Darragon, Manierisme en crise: le "Christ en gloire" de Rosso Fiorentino Citta di Castello 1528-1530). (Collection Academie de France -a Rome, 6), Rome, 1983, in Renaissance Quarterly, 38, 1, Spring, 1985.
"Introduction" to Charlap-Roseman-Ryan, exhibition catalogue, Vassar College Art Gallery, Poughkeepsie, 1983.
Review of Edward J. Olszewski, with the assistance of Jane Glaubinger, The Draftsman's Eve: Late Italian Renaissance Schools and Styles, Cleveland, the Cleveland Museum of Art, in cooperation with the Indiana University Press, Bloomington, 1981, in Renaissance Quarterly, 35, 4, Winter, 1982.
Review of Felton Gibbons, Catalogue of Italian Drawings in the Art Museum, Princeton University, Princeton University Press, 1977, in Renaissance Quarterly, 32, 1, Spring, 1979.
Review of The Farnese Hours, The Pierpont Morgan Library, New York, Introduction and commentaries by Webster Smith, New York, 1976, in The Art Bulletin, 61, 1, March, 1979.
"A Drawing by Rosso Fiorentino of Judith and Holofernes," Los Angeles County Museum of Art Bulletin, 24, 1978.
Introductory essay, "Teaching and Learning from Vassar's Collection," and catalogue entry, "Florentine Painting, Mid-Sixteenth Century, The Expulsion of Adam and Eve," in Promised Gifts, exhibition catalogue, Vassar College, 1977.
"Fontainebleau: Fruit of a Royal Commitment," Art News, 72, 5, May, 1973.
"Rosso in France," Actes du Collogue Internationale sur l'Art de Fontainebleau (Fontainebleau at Paris, 18. 19, 20 October 1972), edited by Andre Chastel, Paris, 1975.
"Some Drawings by Salviati formerly attributed to Rosso Fiorentino," Master Drawings, 9, I, 1971.
Catalogue entries on works attributed to Verrocchio, ,Jacopo Sansovino, Tacca, and Sustermans, in The Italian Heritage, exhibition catalogue, Committee to Rescue Italian Art (CRIA), Wildenstein's, New York, 1967.
"Lappoli, Alfani, Vasari, and Rosso Fiorentino," The Art Bulletin, 108, 1966, 168-180.
"Drawings by Rosso Fiorentino in the British Museum," The Burlington Magazine, 108, 1966, 168-180.
"Some Drawings by Rosso Fiorentino," The Burlington Magazine, 103, 1951, 446-454.
Conference Papers, Lectures, Panels:
"On Rosso's Volterra Deposition and Other Tragedies," paper given at symposium, Il Rosso a Volterra, Volterra, Centro Studi "Santa Maria Maddalena," 23 September 1994.
"The Print images of Rosso Fiorentino," inaugural Mary Stansbury Ruiz Memorial Lecture, Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, University of California Los Angeles, 23 April 1989.
"The Making of the Rosso Exhibition," Talk to the Boston Vassar Club, at Wellesley College Faculty Club, 4 May 1988.
"The Late Work of Rosso Fiorentino, " Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, 7 November 1983.
"The 'opinione contraria' of Rosso Fiorentino: An Investigation into the Fortune, Fame, and Fate of a Renaissance Artist," Princeton University, 12 October 1983.
Respondent to papers given at the Woman's Session, College Art Association of America meetings, Washington, D.C., 2 February 1979.
"Rosso Fiorentino and the Conceits of Florentine Painting around 1520," The National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., 19 June 1977.
Earlier version of the same, The Walters Art Gallery, Baltimore, 25 February 1974.
"Rosso's Roman Manners," Brown University, 3 March 1973.
"Rosso in France," College de France, Paris, 18 October 1972, paper given at the Colloque International sur l'Art de Fontainebleau, Paris, College de France and Fontainebleau, Château, 18-20 October 1972.
"Rosso in France: The Unseen Master," The Frick Collection, New York, 7 October 1972.
Access
Student material in boxes 6 and 14 are restricted. Otherwise, this collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
SEE: The Papers of
William K. Rose
.
Scope and Content Note
The Papers of Eugene Carroll document Carroll's career as a Vassar professor, chair of the college's art history department, and his scholarly and curatorial pursuits focused on the study of the Italian mannerist painter, Rosso Fiorentino. Teaching files include handwritten notes and syllabi, some of which document Vassar academic culture at the time of Carroll's tenure. Correspondence files document his personal, academic, and professional life, including correspondence with colleagues from a range of academic and cultural institutions. Correspondence includes documentation regarding curatorial and general exhibition activities, advice to colleagues in the field of art history, and research efforts, including European travel related to Carroll's research on Fiorentino. Correspondence files after 2000 include copies of emails, both to and from Carroll. The papers also contain reference and research files, travel documentation including scrapbooks, photographic prints, date books and journals.
The collection includes selected holdings from the Papers of W.K. Rose, once held by Eugene Carroll, executor of the Rose estate. Subseries in both the Carroll and Rose papers contain correspondence, biographical files, subject files, writings, printed materials, photographic prints, journals, datebooks, scrapbooks, and realia.
See the associated guide to the Papers of W.K. Rose for additional holdings related to materials held in Series 1, Papers of William K. Rose.
Subject Headings
Names:
Bedford, Agnes; Braybrooke, June, 1920-1994; Chisholm, Anne; Denson, Alan; Hicks, Granville, 1901-1982; Janschka, Fritz, 1919-; Lafourcade, Bernard; Mason, Ellsworth; Nochlin, Linda; Pope-Hennessy, John Wyndham, Sir, 1913-1994; Schafer, R. Murray; Shoemaker, Innis H.
Organizations:
Vassar College; National Gallery of Art (U.S.)
Subjects:
Archaeology; Art--16th century; Mannerism (Art)
Places:
Great Britain; Italy; Mexico
Document Types:
Audiotapes; Clippings; Diaries; Legal instruments; Manuscripts; Photographs; Realia; Scrapbooks
VCL Categories
Art and Artists
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, March 2018.
Acquisition Information
The Papers of Eugene A. Carroll, including selected holdings of William K. Rose as described in this finding aid, came as a bequest from the estate of Eugene A. Carroll to Vassar College in 2017.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, the Papers of William K. Rose, and the Papers of Eugene A. Carroll. The Rose Papers contain nine subseries. The Carroll Papers contain eight subseries.
Correspondents of note and correspondent files of substantial volume are arranged alphabetically by name, otherwise the series is arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically, as titled by the creator.
Series List
- Series I. Papers of Eugene A. Carroll
  - Correspondence, 1955-2012; (Box 3, 7-12)
  - Biography, 1949-1993; (Box 13)
  - Journals/Scrapbooks, 1890-2014; (Box 13-14)
  - Subject Files, 1944-2014; (Box 5-6)
  - Writings, 1953-2011; (Box 3, 6)
  - Printed Materials, 1968-1981; (Box 3, 6)
  - Realia, undated; (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1944-2005; (Box 14)
- Series II. Papers of William K. Rose
  - Correspondence, 1958-1975; (Box 1-2)
  - Biographical, 1924-1968; (Box 3, 4)
  - Journals, 1958-1965; (Box 4)
  - Subject Files, 1957-1972; (Box 3, 4)
  - Writings, 1936-1969; (Box 3, 4)
  - Printed Materials, 1967; (Box 4)
  - Realia, undated; (Box 4)
  - Audiotape, 1967; (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1926-1968; (Box 4-5)
Container List
- SERIES I. Papers of Eugene A. Carroll, 1890-2014
  - Correspondence, 1955-2012
    - General, to EAC, 1968-1976 (7.1-7.31)
    - General, to EAC, 1976-1983 (8.1-8.35)
    - General, to EAC, 1984-1994 (9.1-9.32)
    - General, to EAC, 1995-2003 (10.1-10.27)
    - Allen, Gerry and Gayle, 1998-2008 (10.28)
    - Askew, Pamela, 1985 (10.29)
    - Barnett, James, 2003-2007 (10.3)
    - Braybrooke, June, 1968-1969 (10.31-10.53)
    - Bedford, Agnes, 1968-1969 (11.1)
    - Cook-Barber, Leila, 1968-1984 (11.2-11.6)
    - Costamagna, Philippe, 1988 (11.7)
    - Cuno, James, 1983-1997 (11.8)
    - Dean, Dorothy, 1970-1976 (11.9)
    - Denson, Alan, 1970 (3.1)
    - Finkelpearl, Kitty and Phil, 1968-1984 (3.20-3.21)
    - Finkelpearl, Tom, 1989 (11.1)
    - Frantz, Andrew Gibson, 1972 (11.11)
    - Harper, Philip Rathbun, 1979 (11.12)
    - Hawkins, Harriet, 1971-1993 (3.22-3.23)
    - Hennessy, Sir John Pope, 1974 (11.13)
    - Janschka, Fritz and Aichele, Porter, 1974-2015 (11.14-11.19)
    - Karpinski, Caroline, 1989-2001 (11.2)
    - Kestler, Richard, 1978 (11.21)
    - Lee, John (Tibor deNagy Gallery), 1983 (11.22)
    - McAndrews, John and Betty, 1969-1982 (11.23)
    - Morrison, Marie, 1972-1994 (11.24)
    - Mundy, James, 1973-1978 (11.25)
    - Pooler, Jack, 1970-1975 (11.26)
    - Posner, Donald, 1972 (11.27)
    - Potter, Margaret, 1976-1992 (11.28-11.34)
    - Russell, Diane, 1984-2003 (11.35-11.36)
    - Saganic, Livio, 1986 (11.37)
    - Shoemaker, Innis, 1968-2003 (11.38-11.40)
    - Smith, Joshua, 1970-1976 (11.41)
    - Turner, John, 1994-2000 (11.42)
    - Voss, Susan, 1982-2012 (11.43-11.44)
    - Whittlesey, Margaret, 1969-1999 (11.45-11.47, 12.1-12.35)
    - General, from EAC, 1975-1992 (12.36)
    - To parents, Fulbright Scholarship year, 1955 (12.37-12.39)
  - Biographical, 1949-1993
    - Certificate, Harris Teachers College, 1952 (13.1)
    - Curriculum vitae, Eugene A. Carroll, 1966 (13.2)
    - IDs, driver's license, Vassar ID's, 1971-1993 (13.3)
    - Scrapbook, Carroll family, 1890-2000 (15)
    - Yearbook, Teachers College, 1949, 1951 (13.4-13.5)
    - Yearbook, high school, 1946-1947 (13.6-13.7)
  - Journals/Scrapbooks, 1890-2014
    - 1963-1965 diaries (13.8)
    - Autograph books, 1941 -1944 (13.9)
    - Daily Diaries, 1988-1991 (13.10-13.15)
    - Datebooks, 1958-2014 (13.16-14.1)
    - [RESTRICTED] Grade books, 1965-1999 (14.2-14.3)
    - Phone/Address books (14.4)
    - Scrapbook, color prints, published in The Dial, undated (14.5)
    - Travel diaries, postcards, 1957-1981 (14.6 14.7)
  - Subject Files, 1944-2014
    - 16th c. Architecture (5.21)
    - 16th c. Italian painting, Sydney Freedberg (5.22)
    - 16th c. Venetian Painters (5.23)
    - Adams, Janis / Brown, Jane, 1969-1970 (5.24)
    - Archaeology of the Roman Empire, Prof. Hanfmann (5.25)
    - Artwork, by Shana M. Dressler, 1989 (5.26)
    - Baroque painting in Northern Europe, Rosenberg (5.27)
    - Coleman, Robert, 1996 (5.28)
    - Committee, Experimental College, Vassar, 1968 (5.29)
    - Committee, Honors subcommittee, Vassar, 1968 (5.3)
    - Committee on Research, Vassar, 1979-1980 (5.31)
    - Committee to Rescue Italian Art, 1967-1968 (5.32)
    - Faculty fellowships, Vassar, 1967-1968 (5.33-5.35)
    - Fellowship, W.K. Rose, 1969 (5.36)
    - Fine Print Fair, 1987-1990 (5.37)
    - Florence, Siena (5.38)
    - Fontainebleau et Paris, print images of Rosso Fiorentino, talks, circa 1970-1979 (5.39-5.40)
    - Fulbright notes (5.41)
    - Fulbright scholarship, 1969 (5.42)
    - Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, 1982-1983 (5.43)
    - Italian Renaissance Literature (5.44)
    - Lecture engagements, 1984-1988 (5.45)
    - Leonardo lecture, Powerpoint file, 2014 (5.46)
    - Northern Influence on Italian Art (5.47)
    - New York University art history panel, 1970 (5.48)
    - Oriental art, Benjamin Rowland (5.49)
    - Paleography (5.5)
    - Publishing agreement, Garland Publishing, The Drawings of Rosso Fiorentino, 1975 (5.51)
    - Publishing Houses, 1979-1995 (5.52-6.2)
    - Renaissance history (6.3)
    - Rome, notes (6.4)
    - Roman art (6.5)
    - Roman mosaics (6.6)
    - Rose estate-includes correspondence, 1970-1971 (6.7)
    - Rose estate-gift of W.K. Rose Papers to Vassar College, 2008 (6.8)
    - Rose Estate documentation, 1968-1971 (6.9-6.12, 3.8)
    - Rose Estate, estate appraisals, 1970-1972 (6.13)
    - Rose Estate, legal, 1968-1971 (6.14)
    - Rose Estate, Rose Fellowship, 1968-1969 (6.15, 3.9)
    - Rose Estate, Memorial Service for W.K. Rose, memorial text drafts, 1968 (6.16-6.18, 3.10, 3.11)
    - Rose, scrapbook made by EAC about W.K. Rose, 1944-1971 (6.19-6.22)
    - Teaching and research offers, 1951-1991 (6.23-6.25)
    - Typist, dispute over manuscript project, 1980 (6.26)
    - Umbria trip, itinerary, 2007 (6.27)
    - Vassar, post tenure review, 1971-1998 (6.28-6.34)
    - Vassar tenure review, 1981-1992 (6.35-6.36)
    - Venice, undated (6.37)
    - [RESTRICTED] Letters of recommendation, for colleagues and students, 1979-1993 (6.38-6.40)
  - Writings, 1953-2011
    - "A Crucifixion Drawing by Pellegrino Tibaldi," (MS), undated (6.41)
    - "A Drawing by Rosso Fiorentino of Judith and Holofernes," Los Angeles Museum of Art, Bulletin, 1978 (3.12)
    - "A History of the Art Department at Vassar College, from 1930s Onward,", 2011 (6.42)
    - "A Silverpoint Portrait by Rosso Fiorentino and General Consideration of Fiorentino's Style,", 1957 (6.43)
    - Book review-"The Farnese Hours, Pierpont Morgan Library," Art Bulletin, 1979 (6.44)
    - Book review-"French Renaissance Prints from the Bibliotheque Nationale de France," Print Quarterly, 1995 (6.45)
    - "Drawings by Rosso Fiorentino in The British Museum," The Burlington Magazine, 1966 (3.13)
    - "Lappoli, Alfani, Vasari, and Rosso Fiorentino," reprint, The Art Bulletin, 1967 (3.14)
    - "Printmaking in Renaissance France," off print, Print Quarterly XII, 1995 (6.46)
    - "Roman Painting, 1520-1527,", 1957 (6.47)
    - "Rosso in France," off print, Actes du Colloque International sur l'Art de Fontainebleau, 1972 (6.48)
    - "Some Drawings by Rosso Fiorentino," off print, The Burlington Magazine, 1961 (3.15)
    - "Some Drawings by Salviati Formerly Attributed to Rosso Fiorentino," Master Drawings, 1971 (6.49)
    - "The Tau Cross of Rosso's Volterra Deposition," Source Notes in the History of Art, 1997 (6.5)
    - Writings, Others, 1953-1977
      - "Rosso Fiorentino's ‘Sposalizio' in San Lorenzo," by Graham Smith, off print, Pantheon, 1976 (3.16)
      - "Moses and the Daughters of Jethro by Rosso Fiorentino," by Graham Smith, offprint, Pantheon, 1977 (3.17)
      - "Raphael: The Stanza Della Segnatura in the Vatican," by Sidney Freedberg, 1953 (6.51)
      - The Question of Fetti as Fresco Painter…" by Pamela Askew, reprint, The Art Bulletin, 1968 (3.18)
  - Printed Materials, 1968-1981
    - Art prints, misc., undated (3.19)
    - Catalog, Outstanding Dissertations in the Fine Arts, Garland Publishing, 1975 (6.52)
    - Vassar Journal, dedicated to W.K. Rose, 1968 (6.53)
    - Vassar Quarterly, Winter, Spring/Summer, 1981 (6.54)
  - Realia, undated
    - Toy bear, black satin cap with tassel (14.8)
  - Photographic Prints, 1944-2005
    - Photographs, including "50th Birthday Book,", circa 1960-1989 (14.9-14.12)
    - Scrapbook, including photos, correspondence, ephemera, 1944-2005 (14.13-14.17)
    - Slides, teaching materials, undated (14.18)
- SERIES II. Papers of William K. Rose, 1924-1974
  - Correspondence, 1958-1974
    - to EAC from WKR, 1966-1968 (1.1-1.7)
    - from EAC to WKR, 1966-1968 (1.1-1.9)
    - General, to WKR, 1958-1974 (1.1-1.11)
    - Chisholm, Anne, 1974 (1.1-1.13)
    - Denson, Alan, 1970 (1.1-1.14)
    - Finkelpearl, Tom, 1968 (1.1-1.15)
    - Hicks, Granville, 1968 (1.1-1.16)
    - Lafourcade, Bernard, 1969 (1.1-1.17)
    - Mason, Ellsworth, 1968 (1.1-1.18)
    - Schafer, R. Murray, 1968 (1.1-1.19)
  - Biographical, 1924-1968
    - Celebrity autograph book, circa 1930-1939 (3.2)
    - Certificates, birth, death; library card, press ID, 1924-1968 (4.1)
    - Certificate, Board of Ed., California, 1936 (4.2)
    - Certificate, Cornell Univ., Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society, 1947 (3.3)
    - ID cards, Longshoreman, 1944 (4.3)
    - Passports, 1952-1966 (4.4)
    - Yearbooks, high school, 1937-1940 (4.5-4.8)
  - Journals, 1958-1965
    - 1958-1965 (4.9-4.11)
    - Greece, undated (4.12)
    - Sardinia, circa 1960-1969 (4.13)
  - Subject Files, 1957-1972
    - "Letters of Wyndham Lewis," royalty statements, 1963, 1972 (4.14)
    - "The Men of 1914," publishing contracts, 1964-1965 (3.6-3.7)
    - Trust and Estate documentation, Rosenberg Estate, 1957-1965 (3.4)
    - Wees, William, Guggenheim Foundation application, 1965 (4.15)
  - Writings, 1936-1969
    - "Iris Murdoch, Informally," Harper's Bazaar, includes agreement for purchase of literary material, 1969 (3.5)
    - "Pound and Lewis: The Crucial Years," (MS), 1969 (4.16)
    - "The Rosenberg Gazette,", 1936 (4.17)
  - Printed Materials, 1967
    - "Abelard as Autobiographer: The Motives and Meaning of His Story of Calamities," by Mary M. McLaughlin, inscribed to W.K. Rose, 1967 (4.18)
  - Realia, undated
    - Wallets (3) (4.19)
  - Audiotape, 1967
    - Iris Murdoch interview with W.K. Rose, 1 7/8 ipm reel to reel tape, 11/23/1967 (4.2)
  - Photographs, 1926-1968
    - Friends, Christmas, 1966 (4.21)
    - Friends, colleagues, circa 1950-1969 (4.22-4.24)
    - Friends, colleagues-scrapbook, "Summer of 1955," (4.25)
    - Friends, Braybrooke, June, 1962-1965 (4.26)
    - Friends, Hawkins, T.H., 1965 (4.27)
    - Friends, Mercer, Caroline, and others, 1960 (4.28)
    - Friends, Nochlin, Linda and Pommer, Richard, wedding, 1968 (4.29)
    - Friends, Pierce, Hubbel, 1962 (4.3)
    - Friends, Family, Colleagues-scrapbook, circa 1950-1969 (4.31-4.33)
    - Friends, W.K. Rose and Eugene A. Carroll, undated (4.34)
    - Family portraits, including image of Rube Goldberg, circa 1926-1969 (4.35-4.40)
    - Egypt, 1964 (4.41-4.43)
    - France, Spain, UK, circa 1950-1969 (4.44)
    - Greece, Italy, (negatives), 1960 (4.45)
    - Ireland, circa 1960-1969 (4.46)
    - Italy, 1953, circa 1960-1969 (4.47-4.49)
    - Italy, scrapbook, 1957 (5.1)
    - Italy, Venice Biennale, 1964 (5.2)
    - Italy, circa 1950-1969 (5.3-5.4)
    - Mexico, 1968 (5.5)
    - Mexico City, 1968 (5.6)
    - Russia, 1959 (5.7)
    - Sicily, circa 1960-1969 (5.8)
    - U.K., 1958-1964 (5.9-5.11)
    - Unidentified headshots (5.12)
    - Unidentified negatives, circa 1960-1969 (5.13-5.14)
    - Unidentified b/w snapshots, 1968 (5.15)
    - Vassar snapshots, negatives, circa 1960-1969 (5.16)
    - W.K. Rose, undated (5.17)
    - W.K. Rose, London, 1964 (5.18)
    - W.K. Rose, photocopy, circa 1940-1949 (5.19)
    - W.K. Rose and EAC, 1966-1968 (5.2)